Hazaq Naiem

Hazac

Hazaq.naeem@gmail.com

https://linkedin.com/in/hazaq-me/



+971 50 366 9640



https://github.com/hazaq

PROFILE

I am an AWS certified professional and a Red Hat certified engineer with more then 7 years of experience. I started my career as a member of technical support team monitoring, debugging, troubleshooting open source software and later building high availability solutions for these software. With the revolution of DevOps and Cloud, I worked with development teams to rearchitect applications to utilize the maximum potential of Cloud. I have worked with enterprise Cloud solutions for a major part of my career.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Well versed with Cloud computing technologies. Experienced in AWS architecture, specifically in deploying highly available and fault tolerant applications and migrating production workloads to the Cloud.
 - CloudFormation, AWS CDK, troposphere
 - IAM, VPC, CloudFront, Route53

- EC2, RDS, ELB, Lambda
- SES, SQS, SNS
- Expert in designing, enhancing and administering, security and performance focused system architectures based on enterprise Linux.
 - Red Hat Enterprise Linux
 - SUSE Linux Enterprise Server

- · Windows Server
- Amazon Linux
- Experienced in the design and implementation of fully automated Continuous Integration, Continuous Deployment pipelines and DevOps processes for agile projects.
 - BASH, PowerShell, Python
 - Ansible, AWS SSM State Manager

- CodePipeline, CodeDeploy, CodeBuild
- Github, CodeCommit
- Experienced in designing and deploying disaster recovery and backup solutions.
 - · ReaR, rSnapshot

- CloudEndure, AWS Migration Hub
- Extensive experience in a broad range of applications, middlewares, web servers and debugging tools.
 - Apache HTTP Server, Nginx, IIS
 - Apache Jmeter,

- Red Hat JBoss
- Drupal, Word Press, Joomla
- Well familiar with a variety of database technologies. Capable of deployment, basic administration and troubleshooting.
 - MySQL, MariaDB
 - Amaozn RDS, Amazon Aurora

- · Memcached, Amazon ElastiCache
- PostgreSQL
- Familiar with major container and virtualization technologies.
 - KVM, RHEV, Ovirt

- LXC/LXD, Amazon ECS, Kubernetes
- Planned and architected different patch and software lifecycle management solution for large enterprise datacenters.
 - Red Hat Satellite, SuSE Manager

- Amazon Systems Manager Patch Manager
- Possess in-depth knowledge of infrastructure components such email servers, LDAP, DNS, FTP and monitoring tools.
 - Zimbra Collaboration Suite

- · Icinga, Elastic Stack
- Red Hat IdM , Windows Active Directory
- DNS Mask, BIND, VSFTP, OpenVPN

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Cloud Solution Architect, Moro Hub, Dubai, United Arab Emirates

Dec 2020 - Present

Moro is a global digital transformation entity that offers Digital Services, Data Center Services, Managed Services, Professional Services, Cloud, and Business Center Services to enterprises across the Public & Private sectors in UAE and the region.

Responsibilities:

- Interact with the customer to understand the technical requirement and work on possible solutions and services.
- Evaluate customer workloads and interact with infrastructure and development teams to find contingencies and bottle necks with in the workloads.
- Work with different subject area experts to architect a finalized solution for the customer.
- Build proof of concepts for the customer to evaluate and to get familiarized with the Moro solutions and services.
- Conduct training sessions and workshops for existing and new customers.

Senior Solution Architect, Integra Technologies, Dubai, United Arab Emirates

March 2016 - Nov 2020

Integra Technologies is the first AWS Public Sector Partner in the Middle East and is also Advance partners with different open source companies such as Red Hat, SUSE and Zimbra. Integra Technologies is focused on providing Amazon Web Services (AWS) and Linux based business solutions to enterprises in the Middle East.

Responsibilities:

- Responsible for designing, deploying and maintaining Linux based mission critical server and infrastructure for numerous client spread across the Middle East.
- Researching, testing and bench-marking available open source solutions to assess whether they are ready to meet the demands of our enterprise customers.
- Responsible for managing numerous AWS accounts for different customers, implementing security best practices and performing cost optimizations.
- Automate system administration tasks using Ansible to reduce operation time.
- Building architectures for workloads on AWS and migrating on-premise workloads to AWS.
- Respond to support calls and alerts from the monitoring system. Debug and troubleshoot production issues on live environments, provide remote and on-site support.

Key Projects:

Hamdan Bin Mohammed Smart University – Full scale migration to AWS

HBMSU is an e-university with thousands of active students, their applications included PHP platform such as Drupal, Moodle and Wordpress to Java and .Net paltfrom such banner and sharepoint and around 100 server were designated as part of the migration. As the lead architect I was tasked with building a customized AWS Landing Zone and networking infrastructure, rearchitecting applications and migrating the infrastructure.

Sharjah Islamic Bank – Red Hat Satellite implementation

SIB had around 100 RHEL servers distribution across two sites. The architect of the implementation included a Capsule server in DR site and a Satellite server with internal capsule running in the production site. A custom kickstart template was write to provisioning VM and bare-metal machines using forman. Puppet modules were uploaded to obtain auditing and drift management for basic

controls like motd, ntpd and syslog. A customized Ansible playbook was written to ran CIS benchmark for newly provisioned machines.

• **Invest Bank** – SuSE Manager implementation

Implemented SuSE Manager for around 50 RHEL and SELS servers divided across three different landscapes under a single organization. Every landscape required a separate SuSE Manager Proxy because of the strict network restrictions between datacenters. Also wrote custom Ansible playbooks for server hardening to ensure security compliance.

eKar – ECS Cluster with CI-CD pipeline

ekar is an on demand car sharing company, their application was build on PHP and Java. As part of the project we moved the application into docker project, to automate the deployment process and to create a Continuous Development environment we integrated code pipeline, code Build and code Deploy. The code pipeline was triggered with web hooks in the github repository, code Build was used to build Docker images and upload it into ECR and finally update the task definition of container, code Deploy then updates the running docker container.

• **Injazat Data System** – *Red Hat Satellite implementation*

Software lifecycle management was implementation for 200+ RHEL servers. The servers were distribution in 6 different landscapes under a single organizations. All the server were running on Virtual Datacenters and Virt-who was deployed to collect Virtual Machine metadata to allocate proper subscriptions.

• **AirArabia** – Application and Infrastructure Migration

Built on drupal, the airarabia.com web application was hosted on outdated infrastructure and had issues with scaling. As part of the migration we upgraded drupal and PHP, integrated codecommit and Elastic Beanstalk to manage rolling deployments, application scalability and managed updates. Moved the database to AWS RDS, migrated mongodb to dynamoDB, also added ElastiCache, AWS WAF and Shield. Setup application level monitoring with icinga and Infrastructure monitoring with cloud watch.

Al-Futtaim – 2 Node HA Cluster for SyBASE -IQ DB

Implemented a 2 node HA cluster using pacemaker, corosync and HA-LVM. Wrote the SyBase LSB script since pacemaker does not have a resource agent for SyBase. The Database volume was using a shared SAN LUN between the two VMs running on Vmware. fence_vmware_soap was used as the primary fencing method and to avoid split brain situation delay was added to the primary fencing devices.

• State Audit Institute – AWS infrastructure for handling INCOSAI 2016 event.

Migrated the INCOSAI 2016 event application and mobile application from the SAI datacenter to AWS to handle the load during the global event. Migrated the MS SQL to AWS RDS, setup schedule based auto scaling for cost optimization, integrated cloudfront into the application and also ran vulnerability scan. After the event was completed the application was migrated back to the local datacenter.

Qanawat – Digital music service (jded.fm)

jded.fm is a music service application, the core of this application is running on batch of EC2 instances, the requests are handled by an ALB. Due to high volumes of users downloading static content Amazon CloudFront was also integrated into the application. To deploy the application across a large set of EC2 instances AWS codedeploy and AWS codepiple was used.

• **Gulf Marketing Group** – Suse Linux Life Cycle Management

Deployed the spacewalk based patch management solution SuSE Manager. Designed the life cycle management strategy for SLSE and RHEL Virtual and physical machines. Integrated the Salt stack for configuration management. Setup cobbler for provisioning servers. Patched more then 100 linux machines using SuSE Manager over a period of 6 months.

Systems Administrator,

Wathaaeq Services, Sharjah, United Arab Emirates

Wathaaeq and Estemarat Services is a semi-government organization that processes documents for the ministry of labor and Notary public.

Responsibilities:

- Configure and maintain centralized logging system for audit and security.
- Perform regular backups and upgrades on all production systems. Apply security patches on mission critical systems in case of a zero-day vulnerability
- Work with the development team in managing and deploying Linux and Windows based applications.
- Assist technical support team with any server or client side issues.
- Automating system administration tasks using bash and powershell scripting.
- Administration of Windows Server based IIS server hosting ASP.NET based corporate websites.

IT Support,

KEST LLC, Sharjah, United Arab Emirates

Sep 2013 – April 2014

KEST is a local trading company with branches all over UAE while their HQ is in Sharjah.

Responsibilities:

- Configuration routers, switches, desktops and office equipment like fax scanner and printers at offices.
- Provide technical support to the users, monitoring and maintenance of Datacenter.
- Debug applications and report an issues back to the developers.

CERTIFICATIONS		
AWS Certified Solution Architect-Professional	Dubai, UAE	Oct 2019
AWS Certified DevOps Engineer – Professional	Dubai, UAE	May 2020
AWS Certified Developer – Associate	Dubai, UAE	Nov 2019
AWS SysOps Administrator – Associate	Dubai, UAE	Nov 2019
AWS Certified Solutions Architect–Associate	Dubai, UAE	Aug 2016
Red Hat Certified Engineer (160-230-397)	Dubai, UAE	April 2017
Red Hat Certified System Administrator (160-230-397)	Dubai, UAE	Dec 2016
Microsoft Certified Professional (F450-4855)	Dubai, UAE	Oct 2015
EDUCATION		
BS in Electronic Engineering (Major in Computer systems)	Sep 2009 – Jun 2013	
CGPA: 3.69 / 4		
International Islamic University, Islamabad, Pakistan		

Deferences

References		
Khizer Naeem	Technical Account Manager	Red Hat Inc, Dubai, UAE
Emai: knaeem@redhat.com	Tel: (can be provided)	
Ahmed Raafat	Sr. Solution Architect	Amazon Web Service, Dubai, UAE
Email: arraafat@amazon.ae	Tel: (can be provided)	
Ahmed Shawki	Solution Architect	SUSE, Dubai, UAE
Emai: ashawki@suse.com	Tel: (can be provided)	